Okay, so let's talk about conflict
management now.
Now conflict is a difference in opinion.
A conflict is a disagreement.
A conflict does not necessarily mean that
people are fighting and arguing.
That does fall within the definition of a
conflict, yes.
But conflict does not just mean that
people are fighting and arguing.
So don't just think of conflict as an
argument, right?
Or people fighting.
A conflict is a disagreement.
It's a difference in opinion.
And a difference in opinion is considered
a good thing.
That's how you learn, that's how you grow.
You want people to have different ideas.
People have different ideas about how to
perform the work.
Sometimes it's efficient,
right, one person's idea
is efficient, another
person's idea is inefficient.
But that's how you learn, that's how you
grow by learning from each other.
And so conflict is considered a good thing
because it's a difference in opinion.
Now, obviously, conflict has negative
impacts if it becomes contentious.
So that's not necessarily what we're
getting at here.
We don't want conflict to become
contentious.
We want to work in a
collaborative environment, right,
so that we can resolve
these differences in opinions.
Now, one other thing also to
remember, and, you know, mentioning
this in a few slides, I
mentioned this in a few videos.
There's a difference in conflict
management and conflict resolution.
You can't always resolve a conflict,
but certainly you can manage a conflict,
right?
So it doesn't have a negative impact on
the project.
But that's the whole
principle behind conflict
is, you know, don't
walk away from conflict.
Right.
Conflict is, you know, it's always going
to be there.
You're always going to have a difference
in opinion.
Now, the old view was that
conflict was always considered
something negative and
always needed to be avoided.
The modern view is it can be beneficial.
Beneficial for team growth, right,
because people have different ideas.
You don't want just a whole bunch of yes
men on your project.
You need people that have different ideas,
right, that can think outside of the box.
And that's what leads to efficiencies.
That's what leads to innovation.
and that's why the world is growing so
rapidly.
That's why the world is moving along so
That's why innovation is taking place so
rapidly in the world in this day and age.
Because people have different ideas,
people have fresh ideas.
Now, the other modern view, though,
is that if team members are in
disagreement, if there's two
team members that are disagreeing,
then first let them try to
resolve the disagreement.
let them try to resolve it first.
Obviously, make sure it doesn't become
contentious.
Let them try to resolve it.
If they cannot resolve the disagreement,
then in a predictive environment,
the project manager steps in.
If they cannot resolve it, then the
project manager steps in, right?
In a predictive environment, in an agile
environment, the whole team steps in,
right?
The whole team is responsible.
remember in an agile environment,
teams are self-organizing, right?
You have these self-organizing teams.
So the team themselves are responsible for
leadership.
So it's a team that resolves the conflict.
Now, included in the team is the servant
leader.
So although it says the PM here,
really it's in quotes quotation,
quote-unquote PM, they're not really a
project manager in an agile team.
It's a team facilitator.
And they are the servant leader.
and they facilitate the resolution.
They collaborate.
They collaborate with the whole team.
They use the whole team to collaborate
with one another.
The whole team collaborates to resolve the
disagreement or at least
manage the disagreement.
So again, first let the
team members try to
resolve the disagreement
if they cannot resolve it.
If it's in a predictive
environment, the project manager
steps in, in an agile environment,
the whole team steps in.
Now, what are some of the common causes of
conflict?
Well, there's many, many causes of
conflict, right?
Many causes of disagreement,
many cause of conflict,
I'm sure you know many,
many causes as well.
Some of the common ones between team
members, competition.
That's a common cause of conflict,
right?
It's competition, disagreement.
And, you know, competition again,
it could just be healthy competition.
Think of sports personalities,
for example.
they're competing against one another.
Are you having a tennis game or,
you know, a track and field event?
Everyone is in competition with one
another.
They're all in conflict with one another.
But are they fighting and argue it?
No.
But they are, but they're, you know,
it's healthy competition.
So that is a very common cause of
conflict, right?
A common cause of disagreement.
Now it can get contentious.
But again, the whole idea is we're trying
not to get to that stage.
different perspectives, different
interpretations, difference in opinions,
right, the technical opinions,
a technical approach.
This is a common cause of conflict.
And again, I mean, they don't really need
to explain that.
I mean, self-explanatory.
I mean, that is a very common cause of
conflict.
People have different ideas, right?
They want to take
the, they want to do the,
I mean, the end result might be the same.
They want to get to the end result,
the same end result, but, you know,
how they actually get there might be
different, right?
People have difference in opinions.
Communication is a big thing.
Communication breakdown.
One person, something doesn't get
communicated to the other person.
There's a major, that can be a major cause
of conflict.
That can be a major cause of disagreement.
Oh, I didn't know about the direction.
Nobody told me about, oh, there was a
change.
There was a change in our policy.
I didn't know about that.
So that's a major cause of conflict.
Costs can also be a major cause of
conflict.
So between buyer and seller, for example,
naturally that can be, and depending on
the type of contract as well, in a
separate video, right, in procurement
section, right, we are going to talk about
the different types of contracts.
And so, you know, buyer and seller,
depending on the type of contract,
that can be a major cause of conflict,
right, between, you know, vendor and buyer.
And then on a project generally,
these three, this last bullet point here,
on a project generally, schedule,
priorities and resources, right,
these three account for 50% of all project
conflicts, right?
Studies have been shown and these three
account for 50% of all project conflicts.
So schedule, scheduling
people, scheduling activities,
scheduling activities when
people aren't available.
That's the major cause of conflict on a
project.
scheduling activities.
Or just think of something simple.
Ever try to schedule a meeting with 10
different people?
You know how difficult that can be.
And then people have scheduling conflicts.
Then priorities.
What's a priority to you might not be a
priority to someone else.
So people are not attending your meetings
because that's not the highest priority.
Or you're not getting the direction from
senior management, right?
Because, you know, this project is not
their highest priority.
That's a major cause of conflict.
And then resources.
First, not having enough resources,
or secondly, pooling of resources.
Remember in a matrix organization,
there's going to be pooling of resources.
So whether it's machines, people are using
the same machines, people are fighting for
the same team members, that can be a major
cause of conflict on a project.
And so that can lead to
scheduling constraints and, you
know, people being double-booked
and so on and so forth.
So these three then account for 50% of all
project conflicts.
Okay, all right, so again, remember,
conflict then is a difference in opinion.
In another video, then,
we're going to talk about the
different types of conflict
management techniques.